<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Musgrave muzled: or The traducer gagg'd. Being a just vindication of the Right Honourable Sr. Arthur Haslerigg, and all other persons herein concerned. From the scandalous imputations, and forged articles exhibited by John Musgrave.</title>
            <author>Hesilrige, Arthur, Sir, d. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04444</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R180810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617574</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51617574</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175297</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04444)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175297)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2727:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Musgrave muzled: or The traducer gagg'd. Being a just vindication of the Right Honourable Sr. Arthur Haslerigg, and all other persons herein concerned. From the scandalous imputations, and forged articles exhibited by John Musgrave.</title>
                  <author>Hesilrige, Arthur, Sir, d. 1661.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Council of State. Saterday [sic] the 25. of January, 1650. At the Councell of State at White-hall.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.B. [i.e. S. Bulkley],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Newcastle :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Relates legal action brought by Sir Arthur Hesilrige before Council of State against John Musgrave for condemnation of his administration of the northern counties in "True and exact relation of the great and heavy pressures and grievances the well-affected of the northern bordering counties lye under". Also relates consequent proceedings of the Council of State which found in favour of Sir Arthur Hesilrige.</note>
                  <note>Suggested name of printer from internal evidence.</note>
                  <note>P. 21-22 contain proceedings of Council of State.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Musgrave, John, fl. 1654. --  True and exact relation of the great and heavy pressures and grievances the well-affected of the northern bordering counties lye under.</term>
               <term>Hesilrige, Arthur, --  Sir, d. 1661 --  Trials, litigations, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Libel and slander --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175297:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MUSGRAVE Muzled: <hi>OR THE</hi> TRADUCER Gagg'd <hi>Being a Juſt</hi> VINDICATION <hi>Of the Right Honourable</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ARTHUR HASLERIGG, And all other Perſons herein Concerned.</p>
            <p>From the Scandalous Imputations, and Forged <hi>Articles</hi> Exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by <hi>* JOHN M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SGRAVE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>*—His niger eſt, bunc tu Romane caveto.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. B.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:175297:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175297:2"/>
            <head>MUSGRAVE Muzled: <hi>OR THE</hi> TRADUCER Gagg'd, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe Devill, who ſtill repines at the Juſtice of God in his Damnation, doth alwayes meditate revenge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Righteous Power which condemn'd him. But becauſe he is not able to oppoſe God in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he aſſaults him in his Creatures, and carryes on his <hi>Theomacky</hi> with attempts upon weake mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality: And firſt, he endeavours to make us (like himſelfe) ſons of perdition, and ſo deprive us of that felicity which he has forfeited; but where he cannot rule he tyranniſeth; whom he cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, he perſecutes; like a ſavage enemy, who being denyed the poſſeſſion of a City, falls on with fire and ſword to ruine it. Thus that wicked ſpirit ſhare; his malice upon the whole race of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſeduceth us to be wicked, as he did <hi>Adam;</hi> or afflicts us for being good as he did <hi>Job:</hi> undermines our ſoules, or diſturbs the comfort of our lives, and ſeeks to rob us of our temporall or eternall happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Now the chiefeſt adjuncts and properties of the Devill, are his malice and falſehood, which two, furniſh him with Artillery enough to be what he is denominated, <hi>Diabolus,</hi> an Accuſer. From this grand Accuſer (who is both the Tempter and Informer, betrayes us to bad actions, and belyes our good) doe proceed all thoſe Spirits of obloquy, and hatred: who, while they traduce other mens integrity, endeavour to make them, and wiſh they were, as criminous as they pretend to prove them; and ſo, in a manner, contribute to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of ſin, ſtudy nothing but miſchiefe and diviſion, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175297:3"/>glory in the deſtruction of oppreſt innocence; whereby they evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare the Solliciters of Hell, to be tutourd by the Devill, and to receive Inſtructions from that ſpirit of Malignity and errour.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Quos perdere vult Jupiter, dementat.</hi> And ſure ſome Spirit of Deluſion has infatuated this inconſiderate wretch to aſſume theſe deſperate Reſolutions, and to diſcharge aloft this pernicious darts, which may juſtly deſcend with deſerv'd Vengeance upon his owne head; to calumniate and provoke ſo much eminence and worth, and like beſotted <hi>Haman,</hi> prepare the Inſtrument of his own Execution, whileſt the luſter of that luminary which he covets to obſcure, grows more conſpicuous by this eclipſe and all the ſcandalous imputations make up a veile, not to cloud, but cover; not to deface, but defend him from the caſuall ſpots and accidentall blemiſhes, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might have ſollied the purity of his high actions, and great employments: For falſe Articles, are good memento's to prevent true ones: and this occurrence will be a ſeaſonable adviſce to this Honourable Perſonage to beware of reall miſcarriages, ſince forged and pretended ones give ſuch loud Alarms.</p>
            <p>That Innocence (how ſingular and ſuperlative ſoever) ſhould be depraved, is a contingency inevitable in this World, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of good and bad. In <hi>Shime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s</hi> mouth, <hi>David</hi> is a man <hi>of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial. Joſeph</hi> was accuſed of Incontinency, meerly becauſe he would not conſent to be diſhoneſt, and ſuffered for that impiety which he refuſed to commit. No wonder then to heare the clamours of this <hi>Rabſhekah,</hi> who onely vomits out his own ſhame, and proves him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the retainer to that filth, which he hath with ſo much impious ſedulity raked together and delights to wallow in. For all the guilt proceeds from his corrupted mouth, and can be traced no further then his owne ſcandalous Pamphlet, which like a ſoule overchar'd peece, will recoyle in his own face, and beſtow upon him the reward of <hi>Cain,</hi> due to all ſuch, who repine that others ſervice ſhould be more acceptable then their own, and purſue meritorious actions with enmity and revenge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P. Scipio Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eanus,</hi> that admirable Romane, who in a plunge of Publicke calamity (when all their Forces in Spaine were defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Hannibal ad Portas</hi> and all Rome was but one coward) durſt onely undertake the Spaniſh expedition went on Victoriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered all Spain, ſubdued <hi>Carthage,</hi> and utterly vanquiſht <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:175297:3"/>was after all this cited before the Senate, and a Publick charge exhibited againſt him by the <hi>Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis</hi> the ſame day, whereon former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he had defeated <hi>Hannibal</hi> and the <hi>Carthagenians.</hi> But he inſtead of conteſting with his litigious Adverſaries, bad them all <hi>goe give thanks for the happineſſe of that day, and pray for more ſuch as he had been,</hi> and ſo immediately repayring to his anniverſary devotions, drew all the people after him, and appear'd more glorious that day, then when he rode in Triumph through the City.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of this pregnant inſtance may give ſome ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the World, and this worthy Perſon upon this occaſion and be an example how to treat all ſuch Impudent incendiaries, and their ſeditious Articles: which are beſt anſwered with contempt and deſerve no other confutation, then to be neglected: as was the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent deportment of this preſent Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> when he was bayted by a keener whelp of this accuſative Litter, and beſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd with the contumelies of that Arch-boutefeu, who might em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his own manufacture upon himſelfe and creatures, and ſpend all his Soap to waſh his own and their corrupted mouthes.</p>
            <p>There are ſome Pictures which at ſeverall diſtances repreſent dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Formes. Theſe Articles are ſuch a piece of Impoſture: For at the firſt curſory ſuperficiall view, they delineate onely <hi>John Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave,</hi> but after a ſerious peruſall, and a ſtrict examination of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, they evidently betray a <hi>Lilburne.</hi> Our eyes or ſpectacles, diſcern onely a ſmaller Meteor, but by the benefit of a teleſcope, we may behold a prodigious Comment, ominous to the peace of this Common-wealth. Theſe conjectures may be deduced from ſeverall particulars in the Articles: For much of the injuſtice which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrigge,</hi> has principall relation to Mr. <hi>George Lilburne,</hi> and moſt of thoſe perſons which are here excepted againſt, were great ſufferers under Mr. <hi>Liburnes</hi> tyranny, and were Agents and Witneſſes in the proſecution of ſeverall charges againſt him, as Mr. <hi>Wrey,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lampton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Colſton,</hi> &amp;c. as will appeare hereafter. Thus tis very probable, that Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> is the retird contriver, and cloſe dictator and <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> only the trunk he ſpeaks through, a vizard, ſtalking horſe, and mercenary Soliciter: In briefe, <hi>George Lilburnes</hi> hackney, and <hi>John Lilburnes</hi> Ape.</p>
            <p>And now tis time to enter the Liſts with this Hydra this monſter of ſeventeen heads, and without returning any thing to his oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175297:4"/>ſcurrilities (which are but falſe fires, and give no report) bid defiance to his Articles, which though they make a noyſe, and ſmoak are charg'd with Powder onely, can doe no execution and are indeed but ſcandalls in array, and reproaches marſhalled into rancke and file.</p>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The Articles.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>THat Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>contrary to his Engagement to the Councell of State, and Councell of States Declarations upon the Petitioners exceptions, procured lately ſuch in the County of</hi> Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland, <hi>to be Juſtices of the Peace, Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations, Commiſſioners for the Miniſtery, and Commiſſioners for the Militia there, as were known Delinquents, and ſuch as are diſaffected to the preſent Government, and complying with the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Intereſt, as by the charge againſt them hereunto annexed, and another charge againſt them, formerly exhibited to the Councell of Sate may appeare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> upon the clamours of a buſie impertinent, ſhould give <hi>Engagement</hi> of his fidelity to the Councell of State, doth ſhew how tender he is of the ſatisfaction of that great Court, as to prefer their ſecurity before his own honour; and after a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſeries of ſo many yeares active, cordiall, important ſervice, to allow his integrity to be queſtioned, and renew his ſecurity for his future induſtry.</p>
               <p>As for Delinquent Commiſſioners, if any ſuch there be in <hi>Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland</hi> (for in the three other Counties he objects none) tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> underſtands them better then the Accuſer; has had experience of their fidelity and knows the Common-wealth may without prejudice commit Publike Imployments to their truſt: and how diſcreet &amp; happy he hath bin in his election is evidenced by their faithfull ſervice to the Army in Scotland, and by their care and expedition in raiſing and ſending conſiderable and mature ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes from theſe foure Northerne Counties. Thus they were wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his choyce before he admitted them, or were made ſo by his truſting them; For we may obleige ſome to be faithfull and by confiding in them, make many honeſt; and tis more glorious to convert a Delinquent, then to puniſh him. Againe, if there be any Delinquents made uſe of tis to be preſumed they are in places
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175297:4"/>of no great concernment, or joyn'd in Commiſſion with others of known integrity and judgement, who would eaſily diſcover, and over power their deſignes ſhould they attempt to be perfidious; and perhaps that County has been ſo generally over-run with the ſtreame of Malignancy, that there were few left untainted; and conſequently ſome Delinquents were admitted, to prevent ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, (and <hi>that crime which is anon objected</hi>) unleſſe ſuch as <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> ſhould have been prefern'd who by his perverſeneſſe in this private condition, diſcovers how unruly he would be were he backt with authority and credit; and is indeed fitter to ſet his Clients to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the ears, then mannage the peace of a Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>For the giblets and garbage of his traine the Articles exhibited againſt the Commiſſioners in <hi>Cumberland.</hi> becauſe they include nothing but what is repeated here, and doth ſerve him for all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom he is pleaſed to bring upon the ſtage, they will be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently refuted in the Vindication of ſome Perſons more directly concerned in theſe Articles. For in defeating this main body of his Army, thoſe paddees will eaſily be routed; when down-right blowes be well awarded, collaterall ones can break no pates: and if this triple <hi>Goliah</hi> of ſeventeen cubits can be conquered, the reſt oth Philiſtins, without further diſpute, will quit the field.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>being the chief, and leading Commiſſioners for the Miniſtry at</hi> Newcaſtle, <hi>approved of ſuch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in</hi> Cumberland <hi>at</hi> Newcaſtle <hi>as refuſed the Engagement, were ſo andalous and Delinquents; and ſuch Miniſters as were well-affected, without any charge, removed from their Miniſtery, and put them out of their places, whereby be deſcovers his diſ-affection to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by upholding and countenancing the Malignant party in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and keeping under the Parliaments friends, all which this Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner is able to prove and further, refers himſelfe to the Copies of Letters hereunto annexed, the Originals being in the Petioners hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this we anſwer, that Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> is often compell'd to be abſent from that Committee, being diverted by many great employments, and eſpecially by his attendance upon the relieſe of the Army in <hi>Scotland</hi> and taking order for all manner of Proviſion raiſing new I evies and ſending ſupplies of Horſe and Foot; whoſe diligence and expedition in every particular (ſometimes out labouring com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Porters, and other whiles contriving beyond the moſt retired
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175297:5"/>contemplations) is a ſufficient diſcovery how <hi>diſ-affected he is to the preſent government,</hi> which he ſo ſtudies to preſerve and advance.</p>
               <p>If that Committee in Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> abſence have tranſgreſſed, muſt their miſcarriages be layd upon Sir <hi>Arthur?</hi> He might as well charge the Councell of State with Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> pretended Crimes, and make them guilty of theſe Articles. But tis a queſtion whether any injuſtice was done or not, for he onely ſayes he can prove them, but does not. To which we anſwer, we can diſprove them, but will not. The <hi>Coppies of Letters which he refers us to, whoſe Originals are in his own hands,</hi> are perhaps (both <hi>Copies</hi> and <hi>Originalls</hi>) forgeries of his own, or by his infligation; or elſe the peeviſh motions of ſome refractory Spirits, who (like the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcalites) murmur in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and would loathe their food-ſhould they be cramm'd with Manna; Unthankfull men! who are never ſull, or quickly ſurfeit, and are guilty of ſatiety or unſatiableneſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>undertook to the Councel of State to examine the Articles exhibited by the Petitioner to the Councell of State, againſt M.</hi> Charles Howard, <hi>high Sheriffe of</hi> Cumberland, <hi>but veglected the ſame, and came privately into the Country to</hi> Naward. <hi>and there feaſted with the ſaid Sheriffe, who is a dangerous, and moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Delinquent, as appears by the charge exhibited againſt him by the Petitioner to the Councell of State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Accuſer here exclaims againſt Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> for neglecting to be his Solliciter, in <hi>examining ſome Articles as hibited agaiſt the High Sheriffe of</hi> Cumberland; whoſe examination he confeſſes the Councell of State <hi>(to be quit of him)</hi> had referr'd to Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> and conſequently, judg'd them unworthy their conſiderations. And Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> too upon examination, found them ſcandalous, <hi>Muſgrave's,</hi> and <hi>ſuch as theſe.</hi> This is all, ſave onely that Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> came and ſupp'd at <hi>Naward;</hi> as if it were petty Treaſon for a Gentleman to viſit the high Sheriffe of a County, choſen, and ſtill approved by the Councell of State; yet he proſecutes the fact with as much vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, as if they had ſate down to <hi>Atreus</hi> Feaſt, and riſen from the Table <hi>Anthropophagiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>That the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>ſuffers Captain</hi> Howards <hi>Troop to lye upon free Quarter upon the Country, for theſe foure Moneths laſt paſt, and doth countenance one</hi> Dobſon <hi>Captaine</hi> Howards <hi>Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, who obeated the Troop of</hi> 1350 <hi>pound. And when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175297:5"/>was made to Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge, <hi>he never puniſhed how for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Free Quarter</hi> is miſtaken for <hi>quartering upon truſt.</hi> For Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Howards</hi> Souldiers were ſome Moneths without their Pay, which was aſſigned them in <hi>Yorkeſhore,</hi> and ſomewhat long ere it came to them, but now it is diſtributed, and their Quarters (if any did goe oth ſcore) are ſince diſcharg'd.</p>
               <p>Tis poſſible <hi>Dobſon</hi> did endeavour to couzen the Souldiers of ſome of their pay, and Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> was certified as much, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſent for <hi>Dobſon</hi> and confin'd him, till he had given 500 pound bond, with other Bayle, to anſwer it before a Councell of Warre, which he did, and upon the examination it appear'd that not above thirty pound of the Souldiers mony remained in his hands; aſumme far ſhort of 1350 pound. But I am affraid greater matters then theſe would be diſcovered, ſhould we peruſe the ſtory of <hi>Lilburne,</hi> and examine the Records of <hi>Tinmouth</hi> Caſtle.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>That the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haſletigge <hi>gave Commiſſion to</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Brigs, <hi>to be Lieutenant Collonel for</hi> Carlile <hi>Garriſon, and made him a Commiſſioner for the Militia and Miniſtry in</hi> Weſtmerland, <hi>a man known diſ-affected to the preſent Government, and lately caſhiered for his drunkenneſſe and other miſcarriages by the now Lord Generall</hi> Cromwell. <hi>That the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur <hi>gave Commiſſions to</hi> Thomas Crayſtour, Cuthbert Studholme, <hi>Captain</hi> Brown, <hi>and others, to be Captains and Lieutenants in</hi> Carlile <hi>Garriſon, men known to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to the preſent Government, profeſſ Enemies to honeſt men, moſt of them having now laid down their Commiſſions, when they were to march into</hi> Scotland. <hi>And the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur <hi>doth countenance none in</hi> Cumberland, <hi>but ſuch as are profeſt Enemies to the honeſt party. and are for the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Intereſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> (it ſeems) upon ſome occaſion is not <hi>well-affected</hi> to Lieutenant Coll <hi>Brigs,</hi> and therefore would have us think, that Lieutenant Coll. <hi>Brigs</hi> is <hi>diſ-affected</hi> to the State; when the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent, in any rationall mans opinion, doth inferr the contrary. <hi>Caſheerd</hi> he might be upon ſome miſ-information and both the Generall, and he abuſed. But however. ſuppoſe the Accuſer can ſpeak truth, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> cannot warrant every ones fidelity, knowes not the hearts of men, and what tis poſſible they may be afterwards, as this Accuſer pretends to doe, who peremptorily be ſtowes his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175297:6"/>charracter upon all he meers, Thoſe Gentlemen who <hi>layd downe their Commiſſions when they were to March into Scotland;</hi> did it, not out of any <hi>diſ-affection</hi> to the preſent Government, but upon ſome naturall <hi>Imperfection,</hi> and infirmity of Body, unable to endure thoſe many extremities in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which the ſtrongeſt Complexions and beſt temper'd men had much adoe to overcome; and twas an act of ſingular affection to the Common-wealth in the late Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, to lay down his Commiſſion, upon ſuch conſiderations, whoſe heart (as theirs too, no doubt) went into <hi>Scotland,</hi> though their bodies did not, which would have been but cumberſome, not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to the ſervice.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>That by the ſaid Sor</hi> Arthur Haſlerigg's <hi>intruſting the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, and Militia in the hands of Delinquents, and men for the Scottiſh Intereſt, the well-affected in</hi> Cumberland <hi>and</hi> Biſhopriek <hi>lye under greater oppreſſions, then formerly under King and Prelats. And the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur <hi>is a protector of Papiſts and Delinquents, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Subſequeſtrators, and Sollicitours for Sequeſtration in</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick <hi>to Sequeſter Papiſts, Ordered to be Sequeſtred of which the Papiſts and Delinquents doe much boaſt, and honeſt men thereby are much caſt down.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here the Accuſer railes at eleven-ſcore, and inveighs that by <hi>Delinquent's</hi> (pretended) <hi>authorities, the well-affected in</hi> Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, (that is he and his whining crew) and <hi>Biſhoprick (George</hi> and <hi>Richard Lilburns) ſuffer more then under King and Prelates (which is)</hi> he is not ſuffered to raile himſelfe into an eſtate, nor they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to oppreſſe others our of their eſtates. But that Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> ſhould be a protector of Papiſts and Delinquents, is a ſcandall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts themſelves would ſweare to be a lye, and the moſt notorious Delinquent will abſolve him from.</p>
               <p>Sure the fellow intends to erect a new kind of Academy, and maintain Paradoxes. Were he of any Religion. I ſhould take <hi>him</hi> to be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and that he pretends to <hi>Infallibility:</hi> For elſe, with what confidence could he hope the moſt incredulous Solifidians, would aſſent to theſe impudent untruths? He might as well have ſaid my Lord Preſident was <hi>diſ-affected to the preſent Government,</hi> and the Generall <hi>complyed with the Scotch Intereſt?</hi> that <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> is an honeſt man, hath no gall, is a Dove, meek, patient, Prayes for his Enemies, and is in Charity with all men.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:175297:6"/>
               <p>Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> indeed at firſt commenced his authority with a ſevere hand ſuch as was wiſedome to treat Delinquents with; but after ſweetned his juſtice with ſome mercy, the method of all ſuch, who ſeek not game in humane bloud; for which perhaps, the ingenuity of ſome, render him the homage of good language, an argument of their gratitude, and converſion too</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>That Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>hinders and obſtruſts the ordinary proceeding of Law and Juſtice in favour of Papiſts and did take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Sheriffess cuſtody</hi> Ralph Lampton, <hi>a notorious Papiſt, and Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, being under arreſt, and formerly arraigned for poyſoning his Wife; with which</hi> Lampton, <hi>the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur <hi>is very kinde and familiar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Accuſer now is advane't into Biſhoprick and both the Scene and Actours changed: For this Article concerns Mr. <hi>George Lilburn,</hi> as will appear by Mr. <hi>Lampton,</hi> who now (it ſeems) muſt enter.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Ralph Lampton</hi> being under Sequeſtration, much oppreſt by Mr. <hi>George Lilburne,</hi> and not onely he, but the State likely to be cheated of 3000 l. eſtate of the ſaid Mr <hi>Lamptons</hi> did in behalfe of himſelfe and twelve children, miſerably diſtreſt for want, humbly Petition Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge,</hi> and the reſt of the Committee of Sequeſtration, againſt Mr. <hi>George Lilburne</hi> and one <hi>Gray</hi> his Mate; whereby he manifeſted that the ſaid <hi>Lampton,</hi> being a joynt ſharer with <hi>George Grey,</hi> and <hi>George Lilburne</hi> in a Colliety, called <hi>Lamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Colliery and having disburſt great ſummes of money for the winning thereof; <hi>Grey</hi> and <hi>Lilburne</hi> taking advantage of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſancy, and Delinquency, endeavoured to defraud him of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt therein; and when Mr. <hi>Lampton</hi> (upon order) came to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, and atteſt his Petit on, <hi>Lilburne</hi> and <hi>Grey</hi> barbarouſly procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to be Arreſted. Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> having notice of this injuſtice, cauſed the Sheriffe to ſet him at liberty. This is all the grand par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiallity the Accuſer here purſues with open mouth, and Mr. <hi>Lampton</hi> deſirs of Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> no other favour then what the juſtneſſe of his cauſe ſhall deſerve, and a fiſt part for his Children of that which he ſhall make appear <hi>Grey</hi> and <hi>Lilburne</hi> have in their hands, and that the State may redeem the reſt. For his being Indicted for poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Wife (if any ſuch thing were) he has undergone the Law for it, as <hi>George Lilburne</hi> did when he was Arraign'd for ſtealing a Grey Mare. <hi>Loripodem rectus derideav.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:175297:7"/>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>That the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>procured</hi> Ralph Delivall <hi>Eſquire a Delinquent in arms againſt the Parliament, and diſ-affected to the preſent Government, this laſt yeare to be high Sheriffe for</hi> Northumberland.</p>
               <p>This is a moſt lamentable, infirme, cobweb Item, and only char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> with Mr. <hi>Dalavells</hi> Sheriffalry, when tis the Judges, that after the Circuit, preſent the names of three Gentlemen, and the Parliament pricks him whom they think moſt worthy of that dignity: If Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> interpoſed his commendations, or was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the buſineſſe, the deportment of that worthy Gentleman has juſtified his good opinion; for he hath moſt faithfully and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly (like himſelfe) diſcharg'd that place of truſt and honour. But ſure there's ſomething in the Winde, that makes <hi>John Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> thus diſguſt high-Sheriffs. I am afraid he has had ill lucke in horſe-fleſh too, has been too buſie with ſome Grey Mare, and ever ſince quarrell'd with the Aſſires.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>That the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge, <hi>contrary to an Act of Parliament, ſuffered Lieutenant Collonell</hi> John Jackſon, <hi>a notorious Delinquent, and in arms againſt the Parliament, both in the firſt and ſecond War, a great plunderer, to go and ride up and down the Country with his arms, and againſt Law put the ſaid</hi> Jackſon <hi>in Poſſeſſion of certain grounds and Collieries in</hi> Biſhoprick <hi>belonging to men well-affected, whom the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur <hi>by ſtrong hand diſpoſſeſſed thereof without</hi> Law, <hi>and the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>againſt the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall</hi> Law <hi>of the</hi> Land, <hi>moſt arbitrarily and tyrannically did by his power take from the now high Sheriffe of</hi> Biſhoprick <hi>the ſaid</hi> Jackſons <hi>goods taken in Execution, after judgement, and reſtored the ſaid goods to the ſaid</hi> Jackſon. <hi>contrary to all the rules of the</hi> Law.</p>
               <p>Not one ſyllable of this is true as it is charg'd. M. <hi>Iackſon</hi> did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſomtimes <hi>weare a Sword</hi> (yet without Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> permiſſion or privacy) and he had good reaſon for it; For having occaſion to goe to <hi>Waſhington</hi> a Town not farre from his own abode; and Mr. <hi>Iohn Hedworth.</hi> ſon in law to <hi>George Grey</hi> and <hi>Richard Grey</hi> ſonne alſo to the ſaid <hi>George,</hi> having notice of it, they with others in their company, dogg'd him into the houſe of one <hi>Iames Pearſon,</hi> and there inhumanely aſſaulted him, <hi>Heaworth</hi> holding him, while <hi>Grey</hi> made a thruſt at him, which thruſt (had not one Mr. <hi>Moore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft</hi> but it by) had Slaine the Gentleman; This Mr. <hi>Iackſon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaind
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175297:7"/>of and proved by the Oath of three ſeverall witneſſes before Collonell <hi>Wren</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thomas Dalavall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for Sir <hi>Arthur's giving him poſſeſſion of Lands &amp;c.</hi> Tis true, that after Mr. <hi>Iackſon</hi> had made his Compoſition with Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> and the reſt of the Commiſſioners, and had ſecured the payment of his mony, they thought it fit to order, that ſuch houſes, lands, and Collieries as he had compounded for, and was ſeiſed on before his Delinquency, ſhould be reſtored unto him; which were according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſave the Ginns belonging to his Colliery, whereof <hi>Grey</hi> and <hi>Lilburne</hi> had cheated both him and the State.</p>
               <p>The laſt part of this Chymaera, is a moſt egregious miſtake, or a moſt rare piece of Legerdemane. There were, for a debt of Maſter <hi>Iackſons,</hi> certain Goods graſing in his Grounds, but belonged to an Officer in the Army; theſe indeed were <hi>miſ-taken in Execution,</hi> and the Sheriffe being ſatisfied of the truth, delivered the Cattell backe again to one Mr. <hi>Browin,</hi> who was intruſted with the care of them in the owners abſence. Here were <hi>no goods of Mr.</hi> Jackſon's <hi>either ſeiſed or, or reprieved;</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> was ſo meer a ſtranger to the buſineſſe, that perhaps this Article brought him the firſt news of it; but if <hi>Iohn Muſgrave</hi> will have it ſo, he muſt doe things he never heard of and be guilty of <hi>Delinquents arms,</hi> becauſe others <hi>faile to murder them;</hi> when the moſt pernicious <hi>Weapon</hi> is the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers Pen</hi> whoſe <hi>tongue</hi> is a <hi>ſharpe Sword,</hi> and whoſe <hi>mouth</hi> a <hi>Magazin of Poniards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>That the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>is very familiar, and keepeth company with</hi> Thomas Wray, <hi>a Papiſt, in arms againſt the Parliament, and upon ſearch for a Popiſh Prieſt, there was lately found in the ſaid</hi> Wrayes <hi>houſe, Copes, and other Popiſh Relickes, and much Gold and Mony, moſt whereof Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>cauſed to be returned backs to M.</hi> Wrayes <hi>Wife, a Papiſt. And the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur <hi>by his Souldiers put ſundry honeſt men out of Poſſeſſion of the Collieries ſetled upon them by Law under colour the ſame belonged to the ſaid</hi> Wray, <hi>whoſe Debts Sir</hi> Arthur Hasletigge <hi>undertook to pay, (as</hi> Wray <hi>confeſſed) for the ſaid Collieries, being worth ten pounds</hi> per diem, <hi>as the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur <hi>giveth forth, to the utter undoing of the owners of the ſaid collieries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this lowd nothing, we oppoſe this cleare diſcovery of abuſed truth. Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> hath at preſent, and for many years hath had a juſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175297:8"/>and legall intereſt in <hi>a Colliery at Harratton.</hi> For in the yeare 1644 it was Sequeſtred by Sir <hi>William Ermin</hi> and the Commiſſioners, then in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> for the Papacy and Delinquency of the ſaid Mr <hi>Wrey;</hi> and again in 1646 by Mr <hi>Lilbourne</hi> and Mr. <hi>Grey</hi> make themſelves the States Tennants for the ſaid Colliery; and having found the ſweetneſſe of it, labourd to purchaſe the ſame of M. <hi>Wroy:</hi> and they concluded to give him 5000 <abbr>l.</abbr> But afterward, pretending to have got ſome Intereſt from others in the ſaid Colliery, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own power would juſtifie them in any action, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd the Agreement with Mr. <hi>Wray,</hi> and enterd upon the Colliery, and diſpoſed thereof to their own uſes, and ſo defrauded both Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> of his Intereſt, and the State of the Sequeſtration. There was no hopes of redreffe for Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> (for the was under hatches, and the <hi>Lilburnes</hi> then were uncontroulable) till Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> came into theſe Parts, who being certified of <hi>Lilburnes</hi> unjuſt act by Mr. <hi>Wrays</hi> Peititioning to him and the Commiſſioners, Sequeſtred the foreſaid Colliery for the States uſe. After this, <hi>Orey</hi> drawes in young <hi>Hedworth</hi> to ſet a foot his Title in the Colliery (whoſe inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance indeed it is, buth was bought of his Father by <hi>Mr. Wray</hi> for a terme of years which are not yet expired) and they taking advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of Mr. <hi>Wrays</hi> confinement (who ſuffered a judgement by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulc) re-entred upon the Colliery. Of which plot and knavery, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> likewiſe having notice, he reſcued it from their cawes againe, and re-ſequenſtred it. Thus <hi>Sir Arthur</hi> is charg'd with <hi>put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting honeſt men out of their Poſſeſſions,</hi> becauſe he prohibited <hi>George Lilburne</hi> and <hi>George Grey</hi> to defraud both M. <hi>Wray</hi> of his <hi>Right of Title,</hi> and the State of their <hi>Right of Sequeſtration</hi> and did an act of <hi>Private</hi> and of <hi>Publicke</hi> juſtice.</p>
               <p>In anſwer to the former part of this Article, we muſt relate ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excellent device of M. <hi>Lilburne,</hi> who to get <hi>M. Wreyes</hi> eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Harratton</hi> Colliery from him, pretended <hi>M. Wray</hi> had a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Prieſt in his hauſe,</hi> and under that colour ramacks the houſe, took away all deeds and evidences could be met with, Copes and other Church ſtuffe, ſome old Gold of <hi>Mis Wrayes,</hi> her Watch and ſeverall Rings, to the value of 200 <abbr>l.</abbr> the Watch, and a Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Ring, which were raviſht from them by publike order too;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175297:8"/>but the Deeds and Writings (though of great concernment) no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders whatſoever could recover. What ſtrange miſtakes were here, to ſeiſe on <hi>old Gold</hi> for <hi>Relickes</hi> and take <hi>Evidences</hi> for a <hi>conceal'd Prieſt:</hi> That Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> ſhould <hi>undertake to pay M.</hi> Wrayes <hi>debts,</hi> is as ridiculous as to thinke <hi>M. Lilburne</hi> will <hi>diſcharge them</hi> with the <hi>Gold be plundred from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>That the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haslerigge <hi>doth comply with and countenance Collonell</hi> John Hilton, <hi>a Delinquent, in armes, both in the firſt and ſecond War, and aſſiſts the ſaid</hi> Hilton <hi>to defraud the poore in ſundry Pariſhes in</hi> Biſhoprick, <hi>or great legacies given by the ſaid</hi> Hiltons <hi>Elder Brother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this is involv'd another grand cheat of <hi>M. George Lilburnes</hi> againſt the State of 300 <abbr>1.</abbr> 
                  <hi>per annum, viz.</hi> The mannor of Ford in <hi>Biſhopricke;</hi> which mannor, <hi>M. Lilburne</hi> himſelfe cauſed to be Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred for the Delinquency of Collonell <hi>Hilton,</hi> and converted the Profits to his own uſe; and all this while. not a word of any Teſtament or Legacy. But after, when he ſaw himſelfe queſtioned for this, and other tricks, and fear'd he ſhould diſgorge ſome of the thouſands he had ſwallowed, he contrived himſelfe a dextrous eſcape, by rowſing a Dormant Will of Baronett <hi>Hilton,</hi> made upon ſome diſcontents between him and his Brother, under pretence of charity to ſeverall Pariſhes, where by he was to merit pardon for 30 yeares vicious life led with the Lady <hi>Shelly.</hi> Pious <hi>M. Lilburne</hi> proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the s;uite in Chancery at his own charge, and had a Decree thereupon, which the Councell of State may happily retrieve, and examine better the depredation of ſo conſiderable a Compoſition. Thus we ſee how <hi>charitable</hi> maſter <hi>Lilburne</hi> is with <hi>other mens Eſtates,</hi> how finely he <hi>robs the State,</hi> to <hi>enrich the poore,</hi> and had rather <hi>build Hoſpitals,</hi> them <hi>pay his debts!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>That Sir</hi> Arthur Haslerigge <hi>brought Collonell</hi> Hacker <hi>into the Country, who contrary to an Act of Parliament Quarters his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and others, under the name of Souldiers, who are none, upon the well-affected in</hi> Biſhoprick, <hi>and would but pay what they pleaſed, and in ſome places nothing; but upon complains</hi> Collonell Hacker <hi>gave the people no reliefe, but threatned them to have them before Sir</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Haslerigge <hi>for complaining; afterwards</hi> Captain Thomas Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne <hi>brought the matter in queſtion before a Councell of Warre an</hi> whitehall, <hi>but by Sir</hi> Arthurs <hi>power, it could nover be fully heard,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175297:9"/>which if it had, there would have appeared many thouſand pounds kept wrongfully from the Souldiers, beſides the great oppreſſion of free-quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſome Examinations whereof were taken by maſter</hi> Margets, <hi>which Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>keeps hitherto from Reading, and the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur ſore threatned <hi>the ſaid Captain, for appearing for the Soul-diery and Country againſt him, and Collonell</hi> Hacker.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> was the cauſe, tis probable, of Collonell <hi>Hackers</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance into theſe parts, conſidering how behovefull and neceſſary the attendance of that gallant Collonell would be for the ſecurity of theſe Northern Counties, where the malignant Party had been ſo active, and were ſtill ſo numerous. But ſtraight maſter <hi>George Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourne</hi> thinks himſelfe oppoſed in the buſineſſe, falls preſently to diſguſt the Collonell, and conjures his ſon <hi>Thomas</hi> the Captain to aſſiſt him with ſome deſigne againſthim. Deare <hi>Tom.</hi> layes the ſcene with ſome of Collonell <hi>Hackers</hi> Souldiers betrayes them to ſome miſdemeanors, and perſwades them not to pay in manv places. Theſe incivilities make up a charge againſt Collonell <hi>Hacker;</hi> and one maſter <hi>Margets</hi> came busling into the Country, by order from the Lord Generall (as he pretended but falſely) to examine it. All things being prepared, and the day come <hi>Geo: kich:</hi> and <hi>Tho: Lilburnes</hi> face the buſieſſe; Collonell <hi>Hacker</hi> attended alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his charge; but <hi>Margets</hi> tould him he muſt ſtay for it, and both he and his Souldiers immediately leave the Towne. Hereupon the Gollonell complains to the Generall; who ſends an order to examine <hi>Margets,</hi> which was done accordingly, and this truth diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and certified. This is all concerns that worthy Collonell, whom none but <hi>Lilburne</hi> and <hi>Moſſe-troopers</hi> diſaffect.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>That the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haslerigge <hi>to diſſable maſter</hi> George Lilburne <hi>to ſerve his country, and the more to diſcourage the well-affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in</hi> Biſhoptick, <hi>cauſed him to be put out of the Commiſſion of Peace, miniſtery, and militia, and much endeavoureth to Sequeſter the ſaid maſter</hi> George Lilburne, <hi>who hath commonly been reputed the moſt active, ſtirring, and ſuffering man for the good of this nations, both before the Parleament began, and ſince, of any that hath been, or is in the Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the Grand ſigneour Article, to which the former were but Uſhers, and all the reſt a guard and convoy: This is the maſter waſpe, yet quite without a ſting. Twas the diſcharging of maſter <hi>George
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175297:9"/>Lilburne from his shriving employments, that derived a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> upon all Sir <hi>Arthur's</hi> other actions. But ſince that active, ſtirring, ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> Gentleman affects Encomiums, loves to be popular, and ſhew himſelfe; let him ſurrender up thoſe borrowed Plumes, and weare this Charecter, and <hi>ſecond Livery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For his firſt riſe was little better then from the <hi>Cloake and Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher;</hi> and of late yeares an ordinary Fitter was his greateſt Title. But ſince he ſcrued himſlfe into the Committee for Sequeſtrations, by letting Sequeſtrations to himſelfe in others names for ſmall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues, and bying Plundred Goods at under Rates, he has purchaſed many thouſands, and now <hi>endures</hi> the <hi>burden</hi> of being very Rich, and <hi>ſuffers</hi> the <hi>miſery</hi> of a Vaſt Eſtate.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quid eſſe noſtro fortius poteſt Pato?</l>
                  <l>Ducentiens accepit, &amp; tamen vivit.</l>
               </q>
               <p>In the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtles</hi> time, he ſigned and ſent out Warrants for raiſing men and horſe for the ſervice of the late King, and when that Earle was in the North, he ſent out men and arms to his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and this is called <hi>his good affection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was ſo Imperious in his Sequeſtratorſhip, and ſo ſhamefully over-awed the reſt of the Commiſſioners, that moſt of them were abuſed out of their ſtations, and M. <hi>George Lilburne</hi> was left a petty monarch, attended onely with his brother <hi>Richard</hi> (ſuch anothere haughty ſpirit as himſelfe) and one <hi>Tom Turke, alias</hi> Coll: <hi>Midford,</hi> a creature of their own ſtamp, who durſt not diſpeaſe them, leſt they ſhould queſtion him for a murder he committed upon one Mr. <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier</hi> in <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> upon <hi>Time.</hi> The <hi>well-affected</hi> are ſo far from being <hi>diſcouraged at diſpacing of him</hi> that they all deprecate his Tyranny next the Peſtilence, incert it in their Liturgie, and prefix it to their —<hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>That Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge <hi>hath diſpaced all the well-affected men in</hi> Biſhoprick <hi>that were of the Committee for Sequeſtations there, and put in their ſtead one</hi> Thomas Haslerigge <hi>his Kinſman, and a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and doth continue one Collonell</hi> Francis Wren, <hi>who in the head of his Regiment upon his firſt march into</hi> Scotland <hi>was diſgracefully, and juſtly caſhiered, by the now Lord General</hi> Cromwell <hi>for Plundring, and other groſſe and foule miſde-meanours; and one</hi> Thomas Dalavall, <hi>an
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175297:10"/>arch Malignant, and diſ-affected to the preſent Government, who lived in the Enemies Quarters all the time the Earle of</hi> Newcaſtle <hi>had his Forces there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What the diſplaced were, the Accuſer may ſee if he but face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; and who theſe preſent Commiſſioners are he ſhall quickly be informed; ſo that were he a <hi>Janus,</hi> he might employ all his Opticks, and backward or forward behold his own untruths and ſcandalls.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Thomas Haſlerigge</hi> is a Gentleman of ſuch Univerſall abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſo richly furniſht with Forraine and Domeſtick experience. that <hi>every Country</hi> is his <hi>own,</hi> and he is a <hi>Stranger</hi> no where. Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Wren</hi> and maſter <hi>Thomas Dalavall</hi> are Gentlemen no leſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, and make up an accompliſht Triumvirate of fidelity and merit: they have improved the States ſervice to the utmoſt, given ſatisfaction to all reaſonable men, and are every way worthy of their great Employments.</p>
               <p>Collonell <hi>Wren</hi> hath ever been an active, faithfull Gentleman, and though it was his misfortune to ſuffer ſome obſcurity by the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his Souldiers (ſuborn'd and hired thereunto perhaps by ſome mens malice to prejudice the Collonell) yet never any thing was charg'd upon himſelfe, and the merit of his own deportment did ſoon expunge that caſuall blemiſh which tranſlated him only from his military attendance, to doe the works of Peace; nor was he <hi>diſmiſt,</hi> but <hi>lent</hi> us by the Generall; we <hi>borrowed</hi> him oth'Army, and he was <hi>conferr'd</hi> upon the County to examine the actions, and cenſure the Injuſtice of the <hi>Lilburnes,</hi> who not for any miſcarriages, but that good ſervice doe here traduce this worthy Collonell.</p>
               <p>'Tis onely objected to maſter <hi>Thomas Dalavall</hi> that he lived in the Enemies Quarters; and well, tis not charg'd againſt him, that he lived. We may ſay the Accuſer lived ith' Enemies Quarters when he was in Priſon there (as he pretends) and maſter <hi>Dalavals</hi> reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence there was to him parhaps but little better. However, tis to be preſumed he was guarded with no ſmall ſlock of Innocence, which could there ſecure him even amongſt his Enemies, who were more reaſonable (it ſeems) and leſſe injurious, then this Accuſer, who is oblieged to be his friend.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>That the ſaid</hi> George Lilburne <hi>being Surverer of the</hi> Biſhops Lands <hi>in</hi> Biſh oprick <hi>with one</hi> Edward C Iſton, <hi>which ſaid</hi> Colſton <hi>joyned with one</hi> Saunders, <hi>and counterfeited maſter</hi> Duncalfes <hi>hand
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175297:10"/>without his privity for the abatement of a thouſand and odd pounds meerly to couſin the State thereof which cheat and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uſenage, the ſaid</hi> George, Lilburne <hi>diſcovered. But the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haslerigge <hi>much laboured and Sollicited the ſaid</hi> George Lilburne <hi>to conceale the ſaid cheat and forgery of the ſaid</hi> Colſton, <hi>and though the ſaid</hi> Colſton <hi>be a man diſ-affected to the preſent Government and married to a Papiſt, yet doth the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthut Haslerigge <hi>much countenance the ſaid</hi> Colſton <hi>and made him a Commiſſioner for the Miniſtery, and his court keeper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had the Accuſer been as buſie to diſcover truth as to pervert it, he might have been convinc't of this loud ſcandall two yeares agoe. For maſter <hi>Colſton</hi> himſelfe gave this falſe charge, a cleare confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and in Print Publiſhed his own Vindication which gave full ſatisfaction to the Truſtees. Contractors, and all Perſons whom it did concerne, and to which the Accuſer may repayre if he deſires, or can abide the light; where he ſhall find that all the <hi>cheat</hi> is in himſelfe or <hi>Lilburne,</hi> who would <hi>couzen</hi> the World of <hi>truth,</hi> a Gemme more precious then any <hi>thouſands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What ſervice the Councell of State or Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> ſhall impoſe upon maſter <hi>Colſton,</hi> no queſtion but that able Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman will induſtriouſly diſcharge, and gratifie their Truſt by his Fidelity. In the meane time, he eſteemes it next to Publique Employments (of which at preſent tis Vacation with him) to be of uſe to that eminent member of the Commonwealth, whoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe and worth he is many wayes oblieged to ſerve and honour; and would profeſſe as much ſhould <hi>Muſgrave</hi> every day endite new Articles.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>That your Petitioner hath been much Petitioned by the well-affected in his Country, to preſent their grievances, and oppreſſions, and crave reliefe in their behalfe, as appeares by their</hi> Letters, Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies <hi>whereof are hereunto annexed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This contains nothing of Importance, and onely is an Allegory which muſt be thus Expounded. A Pack of mutinous Incendia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that pretend <hi>oppreſſions</hi> to their ſeditious Phrenſies, have made <hi>Iohn Muſgrave</hi> their Bell-Weather, or <hi>Iack Straw, as may be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from their</hi> Letters &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>That your Petitioner hath lately diſcovered ſundry concealed and unſequeſtred Delinquents of great Eſtates, which will bring in to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175297:11"/>the State ten thouſand pounds and more, if the Commiſſioners for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtration made by Sir</hi> Arthur Haslerigge <hi>were honeſt, and faithfull men; but in regard moſt of the ſaid Commiſſioners are Delinquents, and Sequeſtrable themſelves, and all of them diſ-affected to the preſent Government, they doe what in them lies to hinder your Petitioner in the proſecution thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Accuſer has now gone over all his Poſts, and left himſelf no marks to ſhoot at; yet he has more Darts behind ſtill, which muſt be diſcharg'd, and therefore are let fly at randome, exclaiming in generall againſt <hi>Deliquent Commiſſioners;</hi> which had an Anſwer in the return to the firſt Article: for he but conn's his Leſſon here, and begins before he be quite out: Orly tis obſervable here (as all along) that <hi>diſ-affected to the preſent Government, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with the</hi> Scotch <hi>Intereſt</hi> is the burden of his <hi>Song,</hi> and a <hi>card</hi> that is alwayes turn'd up <hi>tramp,</hi> when he would ſomthing, but can <hi>ſay</hi> nothing elſe.</p>
               <p>Indeed here is ſomthing of new matter, and that is his active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the diſcovery of unſequeſtred <hi>Delinquents,</hi> as if he were more induſtrious for the advantage of the Commonwealth then Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge?</hi> But the truth of all he tells plainly in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance, where he Petitions that his diſcovery of conceal'd <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents</hi> may be taken into conſideration, and then no doubt but he will beſtirr himſelf to ſeek whom he may devoure, then ſhall every Rich man be a <hi>Delinquent,</hi> and guilty of <hi>his Eſtate,</hi> when co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe and malice ſhall have a Salary, and <hi>Sinne</hi> have any <hi>Wages</hi> but <hi>Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For ſhould ill Preſidents paſſe without reproofe, ſhould it be permitted once to Scandall with Impunity, and Informe <hi>cum Privilegio;</hi> every one would turn Accuſer, and there would be no ſuch thing as Innocence ith' world: Each City would be worſe then <hi>Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> not furniſht with one righteous <hi>Lot,</hi> againſt whom the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of ſome would not Exhibit their Exceptions: The Thiefe would Arraigne his Judge, and the Offender Impeach his Jury: There would be left no Councell of State <hi>Inviolable</hi> to Sentence or Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, no Lord Preſident to appeale unto.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:175297:11"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Saterday the 25. of <hi>January,</hi> 1650.</date> 
                  <hi>At the Councell of</hi> State <hi>at</hi> White-hall,</dateline>
               <hi>Ordered,</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>UPon Information given to this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell by Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge,</hi> that one Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> had cauſed a Book to be Printed and Publiſhed, and that in the Epiſtle and Charge, the ſaid <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> did Accuſe him the ſaid Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> of breach of Promiſe and Engagement to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and for acting contrary to the ſame, and contrary to the Councell of States Declaration. The ſaid Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> being called before the Councell, did acknowledge the whole Book, excepting onely ſome Errata's of the Printer, which he offered to amend with his Pen, and ſaid he would juſtifie it, and offered to put in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to make it good. Thereupon the ſaid Maſter <hi>Muſgrave</hi> being fully heard as to the particulars of the Epiſtle and Charge in his Book againſt Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> for a ſuppoſed breach of Truſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:175297:12"/>and Engagement by him to the Councell, and alſo for Acting contrary to the Councels De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, concerning the Examining the Charge of Mr. <hi>Howard</hi> late High Sheriffe of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> for the not diſplacing and putting in certaine Commiſſioners of the Militia for <hi>Cumberland,</hi> who were objected againſt by Mr. <hi>Muſgrave.</hi> The Councell Declares, that it doth not at all appear unto them, that Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Truſt repoſed in him by the Councell, or made any faile of Promiſe or Engagement to them in any of thoſe particulars. But doe find that the Imputations therein layd as a Charge upon Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge,</hi> are Falſe and Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: And doe therefore touching the ſaid Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, leave Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> for his due Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication and Reparation, to take ſuch Courſe as he ſhall think fit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ex. G. Froſt, Seer.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:175297:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
